Guide to the New-York Historical Society Library Department Records 1815-2018 NYHS-RG 21
New-York Historical Society
- Series X. Public Service (RESTRICTED IN PART), 1829-2011; 35.58 Linear feet
  The Public Service series primarily includes the visitor sign-in registers for the library's main Reading Room and its separate Print Room. The bulk of these date from the twentieth century, but there are some registers from the nineteenth century. From the nineteenth century, the series also holds a Librarian Receipt Book used to record books borrowed by the members and admission tickets and cards of introduction for non-members.
  Although the series hold correspondence and print-outs of emails with reference inquiries, the bulk of these are from recent years and are therefore restricted and not available for public access. Some such letters from the 1950s-1970s are in the series and are available.
  Reference correspondence for the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries can be found in the central correspondence files maintained by N-YHS; see New-York Historical Society General Correspondence (NYHS-RG 2). Reference correspondence from the mid-twentieth century can be found in the New-York Historical Society Librarian Dorothy C. Barck records (NYHS-RG 19). Some inquiries and correspondence concerning permissions to quote from N-YHS resources, principally that answered by curatorial staff, can also be found in the other series of this record group.
  Late twentieth and early twenty-first reference inquiries in the form of correspondence and print-outs of emails from patrons are currently restricted and are not available for public access.
  - Subseries X.A. Visitor Sign-in Registers and Related Material, 1829-2010; 16.29 Linear feet
    The subseries primarily includes the books or loose sheets that visitors were required to sign when using N-YHS's resources, principally in connection with access to the library's holdings. The bulk of these records date from about 1909-2010 and record both member and non-member use of the library. A few records from the nineteenth and early twentieth century, from as early as 1838, include non-member visits, but there are relatively few of these, and there are sizable gaps in the date coverage. These records hold only spare indicators of individual visits, with no details such as specific resources used. Any such detailed records that might exist are not held in the institutional archive.
    In addition to the required sign-ins, the subseries includes a ceremonial "Register of Distinguished Visitors" that includes signatures from three events: the 1939 opening of the renovated N-YHS building, the 1954 dinner held at the Union Club to celebrate N-YHS's 150th anniversary, and the 1957 event for the 200th anniversary of Lafayette's birth. Other registers include visitor comment books (1990-1992, 2005-2007) on the galleries and various exhibitions. The subseries does not include comment books from specific exhibitions; these can be found with the files of the pertinent exhibition, principally in the New-York Historical Society Museum Department records (NYHS-RG 20).
    The subseries also includes various documents related to visitors and access to N-YHS resources. These include a Librarian Receipt Book in which books borrowed from the library, a member privilege in the organization's early years, were recorded (1829-1853); daily visitor counts from certain periods (1869, 1918-1937, and 1987-1990); and member and non-member admission cards (mostly undated but likely from the mid-late 1800s).
    The subseries opens with the visitor sign-in books and sheets, followed by the various forms of related material.
    - Visitors Register, 1838-1846 (Volume RG21, Volume 4)
    - Visitors Register, 1859-1873, 1889 (Volume RG21, Volume 5)
      Entries for October 1868 and October 1889 consist of the names of delegates to the General Convention of the Protestant Episcopal Church held in New York City in those years. The register has no entries for 1869 and 1871. The entry for April 5, 1872 consists of sign-ins from six Asian individuals.
    - Visitors Register, 1903-1907 (Box 294, Folder 1)
    - Visitors Register, 1908-1909 (Box 294, Folder 2)
    - Visitors Register, 1909 (Box 294, Folder 3)
    - Visitors Register (Box 1 of 2), 1909-1927 (Offsite-box 341, Volume RG21: 6-7)
    - Visitors Register (Box 2 of 2), 1909-1927 (Offsite-box 342, Volume RG21: 8-9)
    - Visitors Register (Box 1 of 2), 1927-1937 (Offsite-box 343, Volume RG21: 10-12)
    - Visitors Register (Box 2 of 2), 1927-1937 (Offsite-box 344, Volume RG21: 13-14)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 1 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 344, Volume RG21: 15-16)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 2 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 345, Volume RG21: 17-21)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 3 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 346, Volume RG21: 22-25)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 4 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 347, Volume RG21: 26-29)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 5 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 348, Volume RG21: 30-33)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 6 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 349, Volume RG21: 34-36)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 7 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 350, Volume RG21: 37-39)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 8 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 351, Volume RG21: 40-42)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 9 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 352, Volume RG21: 43-45)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 10 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 353, Volume RG21: 46-48)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 11 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 354, Volume RG21: 49-51)
    - Visitors Register. Library (Box 12 of 12), 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 355, Volume RG21: 52-54)
    - Visitors Register. Library, 1980-1984 (Offsite-box 295, Folder -)
      Entries for January 4, 1984 begin here and continue in Box 296.
    - Visitors Register. Library, 1984-1988 March (Offsite-box 296, Folder -)
    - Visitors Register. Library, 1988 March-1995 (Offsite-box 297, Folder 1-9)
    - Visitors Register. Library, 1996-2000 (Offsite-box 298, Folder 1-9)
    - Visitors Register. Library, 2001-2005 (Offsite-box 299, Folder 1-9)
    - Visitors Register. Library, 2006-2010 (Offsite-box 300, Folder 1-10)
    - Register of Distinguished Visitors to N-YHS, 1939, 1954, 1957 (Offsite-box 305, Item -)
      Includes visitors from the official opening in 1939 of the renovated N-YHS building; a dinner held at the Union Club in 1954 to celebrate N-YHS's 150th anniversary; and signatures of Marquis de Lafayette's descendants on the occasion of the 200th anniversary of his birth
    - Guest Register, 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 306, Folder 1)
      The purpose for this register is unknown.
    - Guest Register, 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 306, Folder 2)
      Entries for visitors to N-YHS events and exhibitions including Paris 1889 opening, Luman Reed Gallery opening, Mary Dieryck's Politicians and Panoramas, and Hope Cooke's Early Guide Books to NYC.
    - General Gallery Comment Books (3 books), 2005-2007 (Offsite-box 306, Folder 3)
      Entries include comments from visitors about exhibitions including First Ladies of New York and the Nation, Thomas Paine: Patriot and Provocateur, A New Light on Tiffany, Slavery in New York, and New York Divided: Slavery and the Civil War.
    - Librarian Receipt Book, 1829-1853 (Box 307, Item -)
      This bound book contains a record of N-YHS materials loaned to members, the name of the item loaned, and signatures of librarians and dates documenting the return of item. Includes a receipt by Washington Irving dated January 28, 1848.
    - Visitors Log, 1869 (Box 294, Folder 4)
      Record of the number of patrons visited the museum (includes groups such as Baptist Church) each day between January 1 and December 31, 1869.
    - Building Attendance Statistics (2 folders), 1918-1937 (Box 294, Folder 5-6)
      Consists of attendance statistics with daily and weekly totals per month, as well as totals for lectures given.
    - Building Daily Attendance Counts, 1987-1990 (Offsite-box 308, Cards -)
    - Member's Tickets, circa 1860s-1880s? (Box 309, Cards -)
    - Lecture Admission Tickets, circa 1860s-1880s? (Box 309, Cards -)
    - Tickets of Introduction, circa 1860? (Box 309, Cards -)
    - Calling Card Introductions, circa 1860s-1880s? (Box 309, Cards -)
  - Subseries X.B. Reading Room Records, 1949-2011; 10.58 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged chronologically within format.
    The bulk of the subseries includes late twentieth and early twenty-first reference inquiries in the form of correspondence and print-outs of emails; these recent documents, however, are currently restricted and are not available for public access. Earlier materials and logs are accessible. These include the correspondence of Geraldine Beard, the head of the Reading Room from the late 1940s until the early 1960s. There are also a few logs of books called and letters received for some periods in the 1960s and 1970s.
    - Geraldine Beard Acknowledgements, 1952-1964 (Offsite-box 310, Folder 1)
    - Geraldine Beard Correspondence, 1949-1964 (Offsite-box 310, Folder 2-10)
    - Sue A. Gillies Correspondence, 1971-1980 (Offsite-box 311, Folder 1-8)
    - Books Called (3 notebooks), 1973-1998 (Offsite-box 311, Folder 9)
    - Daily Letters Received (2 logbooks), 1968-1974 (Offsite-box 311, Folder 10-11)
    - Daily Letters Received (1 logbook), 1974-1976, 1980 (Offsite-box 311, Folder 12)
    - Statistics of Copies Made, 1985 (Offsite-box 312, Folder 1)
    - Reading Room. Telephone Reference Questions (4 folders), 1989-1991, 2000 (Offsite-box 313, Folder 1-4)
    - Reading Room. Reference Call Log Sheets, 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 313, Folder 5-6)
    - Reading Room. Reference Call Log Sheets, 1993-1996 (Offsite-box 314, Folder 1-4)
    - Reading Room Coverage, 1995 (Offsite-box 314, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript Department. Telephone Reference Questions, 1989-1991 (Offsite-box 321, Folder 1-5)
  - Subseries X.C. Print Room Public Service Records, 1942-2008; 8.71 Linear feet
    The subseries primarily holds the sign-in sheets and appointment calendars for users of material in the Print Room, which was run apart from the library's main Reading Room. The subseries also holds a small amount of reference inquiries, which are currently restricted and are not available for public access.
    - Visitors Register. Print Room, 1942-1959 (Offsite-box 301, Folder -)
    - Visitors Register. Print Room, 1960-1979 (Offsite-box 302, Folder -)
    - Visitors Register. Print Room, 1980-1992 (Offsite-box 303, Folder -)
    - Visitors Register. Print Room, 2000-2002;2004-2008 (Offsite-box 304, Folder 1-2)
    - Print Room. Telephone Registers (2 notebooks), 1966 December-1977 (Offsite-box 311, Folder 13)
    - Print Room. Appointment Books, 1978-1989, 1999-2007 (Offsite-box 335, Item -)
      Missing 2001 book.